Finding Aid for John C. Patterson papers, 1843-1910
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John C. Patterson papers 1843-1910
Patterson, John C., 1838-1910.
1 oversize folders
18.5 linear feet
852135 Aa 2; Ac
Marshall, Calhoun County, attorney, Republican state senator, 1878-1882; contain correspondence, legal files, diaries and financial records concerning business and family affairs and the history of Marshall; also family papers, including Civil War letters of brother, Philo D. Patterson, student letters from the University of Michigan of son, Frank D. Patterson, 1892-1894, and records of business partner William H. Brown.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The provenance of this collection is unknown.
The collection is open to research.
John C. Patterson was born in Eckford, Calhoun County, Michigan on March 27, 1838. He graduated from Hillsdale College in 1864 and from the law department of the Albany Law School in New York in 1865. Though admitted to the bar in New York state, he returned to Michigan to study two years longer in the law office of William H. Brown. Following this additional apprenticeship, Patterson formed a partnership with Brown that lasted until the latter's death in 1895. As a lawyer, Patterson devoted himself exclusively to litigation in the state and federal courts, arguing cases before the state and US Supreme Court.
In 1867, Patterson married Minnie Ward. They had two sons, George Leo and Frank Dean.
In addition, Patterson was a trustee of Hillsdale College, also teaching a course in constitutional law at the college. Patterson served two terms in the Michigan State Senate, 1879-1880 and 1881-1882. In the Senate, Patterson served on the Taxation Committee and introduced legislation calling for the creation of a tax commission. He died May 24, 1910.
The John C. Patterson collection is divided into the following series: Correspondence; Letterpress books; Legal files; Diaries; Miscellaneous business records; John C. Patterson personal; and Other family members and miscellaneous. Much of the correspondence is addressed either to Patterson or to William H. Brown and pertains to their law practice. Other correspondence relates to family matters, politics, and Hillsdale College. Included in the correspondence are nine letters of Philo D. Patterson written while he was serving in Company H, Ninth Michigan Infantry, February-September 1865. Two of the letters reflect on the assassination of President Lincoln. There are also letters from Frank Dean Patterson, 1892-1894, when he was a student at the University of Michigan.
Subjects:
Calhoun County (Mich.); Hillsdale College.; Lawyers--Michigan--Marshall.; Marshall (Mich.); Michigan. Legislature. Senate.; Michigan--Politics and government--1877-1898.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Republican Party (Mich.); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1891-1900.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Indians of North America.; Mexico.; Minnesota.; Montana.; Navajo Indians.; New Mexico.; Patterson, Minnie Ward.; Travel.; Women.
Contributors:
Brown, William Henry, b. 1812.; Patterson, Frank Dean, d. 1920.; Patterson, Philo David, 1844-1903.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1843-1862 (Box 1)
  - 1863-1880 (Box 2)
  - 1881-1890 (Box 3)
  - 1891-1894 (Box 4)
  - 1895-1902 (Box 5)
  - January 1903-1908 (Box 6)
  - 1909-1910 (Box 7)
- Letterpress books
  - 1855-1873, 5 volumes (Box 7)
  - 1855-1873, 7 volumes (Box 8)
  - 1873-1897, 10 volumes (Box 9)
  - 1890-1910, 7 volumes (Box 10)
- Legal files
  - 1838-1870 (Box 11)
  - 1871-1877 (Box 12)
  - 1878-1910 undated (Box 13)
- Diaries
  The Diaries for the most part concern Patterson's law practice with information on appointments and court case assignments. Some of the diary entries are illegible.
  - 1849-1902, 59 volumes (in 3 letter boxes) (Box 14)
- Miscellaneous business records
  - circa 1850-1900, 5 volumes (Box 15)
  - circa 1850-1900, 7 volumes (Box 16)
- John C. Patterson personal
  - Speeches and articles 1861-1907, 29 folders (Box 17)
    - Fourth of July address 1861 (Box 17)
    - Speech in support of the Union 1861 (Box 17)
    - Speech before Alpha Kappa Phi Society of Hillsdale College memorializing members killed in the Civil War May 4, 1863 (Box 17)
    - Presentation of an Alpha Kappa Phi prize 1864 (Box 17)
    - "The Anglo-American" Hillsdale College June 1864 (Box 17)
    - "The Model Man" February 28, 1866 (Box 17)
    - Speech to Good Templars, Marshall July 17, 1867 (Box 17)
    - Decorating soldiers' graves, Marshall July 3, 1868 (Box 17)
    - Fourth of July address, Homer, Mich. 1874 (Box 17)
    - Speech at grave of R. W. Melendy 1880s (Box 17)
    - Speech to (Hillsdale) Alumni Association circa 1880 (Box 17)
    - Tribute to slain president, James A. Garfield 1881 (Box 17)
    - "The History of the Freewill Baptist Church of Cooks Prairie" 1886 (Box 17)
    - Speech honoring the county's dead, Marshall, Mich., Decoration Day 1887 (Box 17)
    - Speech to veterans of the 20th Michigan Infantry circa 1890 (Box 17)
    - Speech to Michigan Legislative Association, Lansing June 1890 (Box 17)
    - Address to Calhoun County Bar Association June 1900 (Box 17)
    - "Marshall Men and Marshall Measures in State and National History" delivered before the Michigan Pioneer and Historical Society 1903 (Box 17)
    - President's address before the Bar Association of Calhoun County January 25, 1905 (Box 17)
    - Speech of welcome to the first annual meeting of the Lincoln Voters League, Kalamazoo August 1909 (Box 17)
    - Speech at Lincoln Voters League, Kalamazoo May 1910 (Box 17)
    - Speech on Battle of Gettysburg undated (Box 17)
    - Speech: Medical Jurisprudence and the Two Profession undated (Box 17)
    - Article: "The Medical Expert and the Legal Cross-Examiner" undated (Box 17)
    - Article on Isaac E. Crary -- the founder of the Michigan Public School System May 1907 (Box 17)
    - Memorial resolution re Leonidas D. Dibble October 1901 (Box 17)
    - Article -- Selecting Delegates to the State's Constitutional Convention August 1907 (Box 17)
    - Notes on People of Calhoun County (Marshall) Undated (Box 17)
    - Miscellaneous articles 1860s undated (Box 17)
  - Hillsdale College papers 1855-1900, 1 folders (Box 17)
  - University of Albany Law School notes 1864-1865, 6 volumes (in 2 expandable folders) (Box 17)
  - Campaign materials, 3 folders (Box 17)
  - Scrapbooks and personal financial records, 8 volumes (Box 18)
- Other family members and miscellaneous
  - Minnie Ward Patterson: Poems, songs and short stories, 7 folders (Box 18)
  - George Leo Patterson
    - Speeches, 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Clippings, testimonial and correspondence, 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Scrapbook (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous biographic data:
    - John C. Patterson (Box 18)
    - Minnie Ward Patterson (wife) (Box 18)
    - George Leo Patterson (son) (Box 18)
    - Frank Dean Patterson (son) (Box 18)
    - Philo D. Patterson (brother) (Box 18)
    - Abraham Duncan Patterson (grandfather) (Box 18)
    - Harriet Wait Patterson (mother) (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous ancestors (Box 18)
    - William Henry Brown (law partner) (Box 18)
  - First Congregational Church of Marshall, Michigan 1860-1899, 1 folders (Box 18)
  - Marshall Machine Company 1869-1881, 1 volumes (Box 18)
  - Constitution and Bylaws of the Marshall Light Infantry undated, 1 folders (Box 18)
  - Photographs, 7 folders
    Portraits and informal photographs of Patterson, his wife Minnie Ward Patterson, and other Patterson family members; also photographs, mainly taken by Minnie Ward Patterson while traveling in Minnesota and Montana, ca. 1902, and while traveling in Mexico and the southwest United States, including images of Native Americans and their crafts.
    - Family photographs, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Snapshots of Minnie, George Leo, child, and dog (Box 18)
    - Mexico circa 1903 (Box 18)
    - Indians (Box 18)
    - Montana; Minnesota circa 1902 (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - William Henry Brown: Miscellaneous notes and financial records, 18 volumes (Box 19)
    (includes volume re: Hillsdale College Semi-Centennial)
  - Appointment certificates, land deeds, newspaper obituaries, etc., 1 oversize folders (Folder AC)